we're polar ice creamery we make a shed
load of ice cream from ben jerry's
haagen-dazs jenny's salt and straw you
name it we make it if you want to see
how we do that head on over to the
channel check out video or
stick around and watch how we make
this ben jerry's chocolate fudge brownie
if you watch our channel
you know that i usually do these videos
on a sunday morning
and that means eating ice cream at 7 7
30 while kids still in bed asleep but
today it's saturday night so i've got a
drink ready to go we're going to dive
into this
ben and joe's chocolate fudge brownie
we're going to look at the ingredients
see if we can somehow figure out what's
going on and there's a lot of stuff in
here and also try and figure out if we
can see the macros see what the fat
percentage sugar percentage is
let's just see if we can manage it
[Music]
so
let's
open this up
i have no nails open that for me
bear with me a second oh let's put some
musaco over the top some nice elevator
music
cheers
[Music]
let's see what this is like now as far
as i remember this is uh this is not
haagen-dazs it's ben jerry's this is ben
jerry's best flavor i used to eat this a
lot as a kid
and it always just used to remind me of
how good ben and jerry's were
let's
dig in it's a medium brown
color it's not particularly dark
doesn't smell at all
it's it is good you know there's no
disputing that is it as good as i
remember nah no but
or maybe i should say is it as good as
ours
no
but there's a bit of brownie there
the brownie's got a tiny little
maltiness to it
so that's quite interesting i've never
noticed that before but
i i'd say this is this is a medium dark
chocolate ice cream
still really good it is still a good ice
cream
so let's um let's have a look at the
ingredients on the back
[Music]
so
let's look at the ingredients i'm going
to put a thing up here half and half
and we'll talk to the ingredients
so we've got cream which is 25 of this
tub
then water sugar condensed skimmed milk
cocoa powder wheat flour fat reduced
cocoa powder
fully refined soy oil free range egg
yolk invert sugar egg
dried egg white stabilizers which is
gargoyle and carrageenan salt vanilla
extract malted barley i knew it was in
there
raising alien agent which is sodium
bicarbonate
and then that's pretty much it then the
whole fair trade sourcing thing
so
of those ingredients let's try and
decide what goes where
so of all those ingredients i think
we're gonna divide them up brownies and
ice cream
and see what we can come up or see if we
can decipher what's what
so we've obviously got cream that's
gonna be ice cream the water is ice
cream sugar ice cream condensed milk ice
cream cocoa powder ice cream wheat flour
will be brownies fat reduced cocoa
powder
either
we'll we'll split it and put it in
both for now fully refined soil that's
going to be brownies free-range egg yolk
considering there's other egg products
in there that's likely ice cream invert
sugar ice cream egg brownies dried egg
white
talk about that in a minute ice cream
stabilizers the guru gum and carrageenan
ice cream salts likely the brownies
vanilla could be either
malted barley is definitely the brownies
raising agent sodium bicarbonate
definitely brownies
there's no more sugar on there so
there's no i would have thought there'd
be like two different types of sugars so
they've probably taken the sugar that we
first mentioned which we put in the ice
cream and we'll halve it
and put some in the brownies
here we go
the weird little list of ingredients
that goes into ben and jerry's chocolate
fudge brownie
can we identify the ratios no absolutely
not we know that
of this tub is
a cream product
we don't know what that is we don't know
what the fat percentage is we don't know
what type of cream it is
and there's no other numbers in there
apart from the brownie where it says 12
12 of that tub is brownie pieces
there's no other way to decipher what
the fat content is if you look down at
the nutritional values
it says per 100 grams we've got 13 grams
of fat but that's including the brownies
as well so that's not just the ice cream
it it would technically be possible if
we take all the brownie ingredients and
make them and then calculate the
nutritional value of the brownies and
subtract subtract that from what's left
we could possibly get close to an ice
cream but what we do know is
ben and jerry's are made to an american
palette so they're made to the 13 to 15
fat ratio ish somewhere between 16 and
18 sugar ish
that's kind of where they land so let's
knock up a recipe based on those
approximate numbers
and see what we can do
[Music]
now
one thing we know about the brownies and
ben and jerry's don't hide this at all
is that they get them from grace and
bakeries in yonkers new york
we i personally highly doubt that
they're a standard brownie recipe and
they're made specifically for ben and
jerry's because let's be fair they make
bloody millions of them
so i had a look online and found a
graystone bakery brownie recipe but
there was no mention of the malt flavor
or the malt extract or whatever they use
in there so i've adjusted that
and added some of that malt powder into
it to try and recreate that multi kind
of brownie taste that
the tub has
and this
is the recipe that i've come up with
[Music]
we're going to put the full
recipe for all this make in the
description below so head down and have
a look but to make these brownies you're
going to melt your chocolate and your
butter in a microwave you can melt over
a bain-marie if you like then when
that's all completely melted add in your
eggs and your sugar get it nicely
combined and then finally add all your
dry ingredients
get it all mixed together nicely then
put it in
a pan i've used baking parchment here in
the pan
use whatever you've got available and
then bake it in the oven at 385
fahrenheit which is 200c for 25 minutes
now this is an 8x8 square pan for that
so you might have to adjust cooking
times
if you use something bigger when they're
baked take them out let them cool down
slightly and then cut them up into
whatever size chunks you want to cut
them up and just let them cool
completely
[Music]
now on to the ice cream bit now
if you watched our first episode of our
chocolate series how to make chocolate
ice cream we very briefly touched on the
different types of cocoa powder
different types of chocolate and i have
absolutely no doubt that there is a very
specific type of cocoa powder that goes
into this
i'm going to use two different ones one
which is going to be the bulk of the
flavor and then another one to add a
slight darker color to it try and
recreate what i consider a medium dark
chocolate ice cream
so
let's get on to the making of the ice
cream shall we so again this full recipe
is going to be in the description below
so if you want to know how we do it get
all the ingredients from there we're
going to start off with our invert sugar
here i've used glucose syrup we're going
to put that in the pan first and then
add our milk straight on top of that
to that we're going to add our egg yolks
make sure they're really nicely whisked
up and combined
you don't need to do the old fashioned
tempering thing but we'll talk about
that another day once that's mixed
together add in the cocoa powder so this
is calibo 24 fat cocoa powder get that
nicely mixed in and here we're going to
add in our skimmed milk powder mine is
crap and it just really doesn't want to
separate and dissolve but just keep
going and it will eventually one thing i
didn't film is the addition of five
grams
of the darker cocoa powder and i've used
the
van gaal 100 it's 12 percent fat cocoa
powder but it's black it's described as
intense black cocoa powder so that's
gone in here and been nicely combined as
well once that's up to 65 degrees c as
you can see from the magical thermometer
take it off the heat and then put it in
a container and from that point we are
going to add in our cream now i've used
uk double cream it's 49 fat if you want
to use whipping cream you'll have to
change the ratio slightly so
if you want to do that just send us a
message and i'll give you an updated
recipe for it
give it a nice mix and put it in the
fridge and keep it in there for at least
four hours once your ice cream base is
nice and chilled take it out the fridge
get your ice cream machine as cold as
possible before you start and then put
it in and get it churning now once your
ice cream is shining take some of your
brownies and chop them up into one to
one and a half centimeter cubes put them
in a nice little tub we're gonna use
those in a minute when your ice cream is
fully churned it should be somewhere
near the soft serve consistency take it
out and start loading it into the tub
along with your brownie cubes
get that full up and get it in the
freezer for a good few hours
well normally i get my nice little
pretty japanese bowl and serve it in
that but we're gonna do a side-by-side
comparison
so back to the plate the old school
plate that the first haagen-dazs belgian
chocolate one was done on that's what
we're going to use there we go
first time
to compare now i've actually done this
one this recipe
is done based on
images memory
and what it tasted like earlier
so
all of that combined is what i've used
to create this
are we close i don't know let's let's
scoop it all up and
[Music]
see we've had to put the tubs back in
the freezer because it's really hot in
this kitchen we've actually been cooking
and our house is brand spanking new so
it just retains all the heat
as you can see they're all melting so
we're gonna have to get a move on color
wise
i think it's spot on
i think the color is pretty much
identical
there's obviously is melting
considerably faster than ours
there's various reasons for that but
we'll go through those kind of reasons
in our chocolate ice cream series so
make sure you like and subscribe if you
want to find out why these all melt at
different speeds
let's try it
[Music]
the brownies
perfect i mean
spot on identical same consistency same
taste
and really bloody good
the ice cream
i mean the texture of ours is head and
shoulders above theirs
but that's to be honest that's to be
expected because they are bulk making
ice cream from cheaper ingredients and
that's where that
powdered egg white comes in now i asked
some other ice cream scientists out
there in the world that we live in
and they all agreed that it's likely the
egg whites or the powdered egg whites
were put in to increase the overrun and
to imitate a creamier taste but without
using any more cream
so that's why they've used them we on
the other hand have used cream so what
we're getting is additional milk fat and
milk proteins we're getting the lactose
and that cream as well to come in
and we're getting a much more luxurious
ice cream from it but it is incredibly
close to the benadryl's actual flavor
i'd say that their brownies are probably
broken apart rather than cubed with
cubed ours
and put them in there but theirs are
much
less defined so they've probably got a
machine that kind of just hacks them up
into bits and then you know folds it all
in as the whole ice cream is being made
we
we don't have those machines we have the
luxury and the time to actually make
them any shape we like so i've cubed
them
but all in all
this is really really close really close
and if you're after the the perfect ben
and jerry's chocolate fudge brownie
recipe i tell you what you gotta try
this one
like i said before chocolate ice cream
is incredibly difficult to get right
it's not really that difficult once you
understand
the ins and outs of it
so
like and subscribe check out our
chocolate ice cream series
thanks very much for watching and we'll
see you next week when actually we do
the next episode of our chocolate ice
cream series so see you then
we're just making our way through the
ice creams actually something i didn't
mention
is
the grace and bakery brownies that ben
and jerry's use in their tubs doesn't
have any real chocolate in it there's no
real chocolate on the back of their tub
so the grayson bakery brownies not only
are malted but they're malted with only
cocoa powder no chocolate
and that's
why mine are better
oh
my face look
happens